being here. Um, I think I speak for both
of us when I say it's humbling to see
how many people show up, to see some
regular nobodies talk about things. Um,
it's kind of weird. Um, roll out a dirty
band coming to a room full of people.
Um, and uh, we had Who was there last
night? Raise your hand. Yeah. Who had
who had fun last night?
>> Yeah. Who got electrocuted at Parkers?
[laughter]
>> Mandatory. Who's getting electrocuted
today?
>> I don't know what
>> Well, for those of y'all who don't know
Parker, I just want to qualify him by
saying he knows more about energy than
anybody I know at a different level. Um,
he knows how it lives, how it moves.
Like he is the sparring coach for
electricity. Um, and anything dealing
with frequency, transformers,
capacitors, like I don't understand. I I
can't follow them half the time. So, I'm
going to refer any super technical
questions about frequency, the resonant
frequency of earth, um, the address of
electricity, the partner. Um, and just
know that I'm going to try and roll
through this and just just tell y'all
how I configure solar and how you can do
it, too. The whole purpose of this class
is to teach you how you can design and
figure and install a system on your own
without any help because you can ask
Parker. The amount of people that ask us
questions on a regular basis, it's it's
a lot, isn't it? And you can't you don't
want to answer it, you know, 48,000
times. You'd like to do it one time and
then record it so everybody can get the
information for free. Um, and my main
impetus for going to teach this class is
I have a moral dilemma with electricity.
I do not think that humans should buy
and sell electricity. I don't think it's
theirs. Um, I think it was put here on
this earth by God for all of us to use
and that people have been selling it to
you and I don't like that. And so I will
give up my time, my energy for free if I
can teach you the only way that I know
right now that you can just snatch it.
you know, you can buy yourself out of
buying energy. Quit renting it. You
[clears throat] can buy pay cash one
time and own it forever. Um, and I asked
Parker to code because he's going to add
a lot to this that I don't know. And he
is just fantabulously dressed.
And
[applause]
>> real quick, can I have Marshall, Bruce,
where's Michael? Joseph, can I have all
my big Where's Dave?
I want all my big battery people up here
so y'all know who owns this place and
who make this possible. This is
Marshall. Marshall is
Can you tell who you are?
>> Yeah, you
my name is Marshall. I started this
company with my partner eight years ago.
Um um we I'm an engineer. He's a
businessman. I came from NASA aerospace
engineering project manager for 12
years. built spacecraft and I decided um
I retired one day. I started some other
businesses and I retired one day and I
lived up in the mountains of Montana and
I said um I don't really want to pay
$15,000 to get power gr up here and I
don't want to pay anyone electric bill
anymore. And I realized that you could
build your own solar system and it's
really not that hard. And back then the
batteries were terrible. There were
they'd catch fire. They're from China
and you know there was some you know DIY
stuff out there but it was it was rough.
So I said I'm going to start a company
to make a very cheap affordable battery
for the American market designed by
engineering methods and acids so they
don't fail. They don't have thermal
problems and whatever. And I was retired
so I was like I have to do this on my
own. So I don't need to pay a big
engineering team. And so I designed the
batteries and then now we've got these
products that um are killing it. I mean
they're the most affordable offgrid
systems in in America and uh with a
10-year warranty. And my goal is just to
like I I can do whatever and my goal is
to do this and provide people the power
to have their own energy. And so Joe and
I have almost the same kind of mindset.
It's a really good partnership and I
really invited him to come out here.
He's great. Um the fact that we just
align in our in our
ideals, you know, I'm a I'm a super
libertarian like Bitcoin freaking like
off the grid kind of guy and you
wouldn't think that from a technical
perspective, but you know, ideals and
techn
they they have a cohesive u you know,
merge in some way. So that's my
background. I I I thank you guys for
coming here. I hope that you learned
everything that you want to know and you
can ask me questions. You can ask him
questions. And of course, uh Parker,
right?
>> Okay. I'm going to introduce uh Michael.
>> When else will you get a
>> When else will you get a chance to pick
Parker's brain, my brain, and the nasty
engineers?
>> Free.
[applause]
You retired and needed solar for your
place. I retired to a van and needed
solar for my place and here we are. Kind
of funny.
Yeah. And then who's next? Do the next
engineer. Come on.
[applause]
>> How's it going, guys? And my name is
Michael. Uh, just so you know, I've been
with the company about five years. I
started as an intern and scale all the
way up to engineering director. So uh
what I can tell you about big battery
products is that
uh I share the dream to make energy
accessible for everybody. And same way
as Joe has been to Costa Rica, I've been
into Ecuador, South America, I've seen
how people do not have power.
>> They cannot power their pumps. they
don't have water and it's it's hard it's
hard to see. So all of these
I probably say all this experience has
been helpful and has helped us develop
the best products not only to to
actually get the best system but also
the most uh our policy accessible for
everybody. And Joe is going to show you
it's pretty easy to install.
Thank you.
>> And next, [applause]
cuz nobody nobody sees these guys. I
deal with these guys a lot. And I have
worked with Bruce for months, months to
figure out the import process to Costa
Rica. Like three and a half months. I
don't know how many different translated
emails we've gone through. Uh but Bruce
is behind the scenes and if you ever get
something new, you're going to deal with
Bruce.
>> So I'm Bruce. I'm the director of sales
battery. Um, I've been in and around the
solar world for about 10 years,
commercial, a little bit down to
residential. Uh, stepped away from it
and, uh, wouldn't come back until I
could find someone that I could partner
with and believe in what their their
dreams were. So, meeting Eric and
Marshall at my time at another company
just led to me being here and I can just
tell you the guys live the dream that
they say they want to chase. So,
>> thank you, Bruce. [applause]
You need to stand next to Joseph.
We have 1920 and 2020.
I love the duel there. So, hello
everyone. I'm Joseph at Big Battery. I'm
essentially director of brand
effectiveness. It's how we market, how
we describe our brand identity, show our
brand identity, connect with people, and
express ourselves in the digital age.
So, basically, it's one of the reasons
we're all here. Joe, Parker, they're
fantastic at such a thing. And that's my
background. And really, a change
occurred where I wanted to do good
things. And seeing all you here is
really a reflection of something good,
something that's worth growing,
something that's worth bringing people
together about. So, it's an honor to be
here and I thank both of you for doing
this.
>> Thank you for having us.
Last thing I'm going to say is if you've
ever seen me on social media, which I
assume some of you have. I'm never
trying to sell you nothing. I'm not
trying to sell you anything. Uh the
reason I'm here with these guys is not
cuz they're a good company with good
products, which they are, but it's
because the owners of the company are
men. I spent a week with Eric and Julian
and Stephanie trip through Costa Rica.
We stayed up till 2 a.m. talking about
anti- Dolubian cultures. Uh, and I mean
they have a good moral compass and if
you ever have a problem out of anything
they sell, they going to fix it quick.
It's not like a lot of other companies
I've dealt with. Uh, and uh, I just say
they're good people and that's really
what I want is just good people doing
good things together. If you get enough
people going in one direction, it's
called a movement. So, with no further
ado, I'm going to do my best to explain
solar energy as I understand it. Uh, I
just call this simplifying solar cuz the
problem is there's a ton of products and
no information. Who has ever looked up
some type of solar thing on the
interwebs?
Did anybody have any relative success
finding clear information?
Okay. Well, that changes today. All
right.
So,
basically,
there's a few things you need to know
about solar. All right.
This is known as Ohm's law, Watts law.
There's a lot of different things that
you can follow this formula. Amps*
volals watt.
Next, you must know the difference
between series and parallel wiring.
Can y'all read my chicken scratch?
>> Yes, sir.
>> I took an SAT one time and it was
negative.
>> Does anybody want any pencil?
>> And if anybody has a question, feel free
to stop him because I want everybody in
here to get this. And some people learn
quicker than others.
Do you want to explain these Parker?
>> No. Yeah, Parker. Series and parallel is
a big thing.
>> It's very simple, but it's I will say
guys, all of this stuff is so simple,
but because it's so simple, it's
remarkably easy to mess up. And you
wouldn't think it, but you got a 50/50
chance. There's only a positive and
negative, but you wouldn't believe how
hard it is to get all the way right
because you have to do very simple
things repetitiously.
>> Okay, we're ready to do
All
right.
So,
for energy to exist, it has to be
defined, right? Kind of like a human
being must have air, pulse, and body to
exist. Energy is really defined as amps
time volts equals watts. I'm going to
explain that for you. Um,
let's take a microwave for example that
pulls 100 watts.
Okay. [clears throat]
Does anybody know what voltage a
microwave operates on?
>> 120.
>> Usually 120.
>> 120. Okay.
This is a formula
in order to solve for something like
what size breaker does the microwave
need to be on? Anybody had to figure
that out before? Okay. So, we read the
electrical label on the microwave. It
tells us it pulls 100 watts.
And you know that plug is 120 volts. So,
you say 100 watts equals amps. That's
our breaker size. We want to know what
that is. Times 120 volts.
So, you can divide the whole thing
120 volts.
What is 100 / 120?
>> Make it easier.
>> A thousand watts.
>> Anybody know?
>> 15.
>> Somebody got a couple later. I can do
it. [clears throat]
>> You don't want to oversize it?
>> Well, we'll get to that in a second.
No, I'd say the 15 15 is somebody
8.3
>> 8.3.
So that'd be 8.3 amps.
>> So what size breaker would you put that
on?
>> 10.
>> Well, the 15 because there are no 10 amp
breakers, but you get you get the point.
Um, and this is not an exact
measurement. This is so you see how the
formula works. But everything has to
have amps times volt equals watts. And I
explain this with a water analogy. Okay.
The watts
are how many total gallons you have. The
energy is the river and the amps we'll
say because amps is current. You know,
I'll say how wide the river is. And
we'll say the volts is how deep the
river is. Because you could have a river
that is 30 foot deep and 40 foot wide
and it would be 1,200 gallons. Or you
could have one that is 60 wide and 20
deep and it'll still equal 1,200, but
the water in the river is going to
behave massively different. You know,
because a wide shallow river is going to
move a lot faster. Okay. And a deep a
deep narrow river is going to move a lot
slower, but it's still going to have the
same amount of gallons in it. Does
everybody follow me here?
>> And you just got to go and understand
what energy is and how it moves. And
then you can learn to manipulate it. But
once you do that, does everybody
understand amps* volts equals watts? Am
I losing anybody? We're going to go to
the next one.
Series. You have two different types of
wire. If you connect in series, what
does it look like, Parker?
>> We're going to go plus minus plus minus.
Now, on that solar panel, there are two
leads. One is a positive and one is a
negative.
And if you look at them, will you go
over and hold those up so they can kind
of see?
If you go over there and look at these
panels, you'll see that it has one
positive and one negative. They only go
one way. You cannot connect the wrong
ones together unless you connect the
same ones on a panel together. Don't do
that. [laughter]
one way to mess it up. Don't do that.
But in series, you literally just take
them and clip them together. And when
you do that, the voltage increases and
the ampacity remains constant. See, we
have volts and amps and watts.
Does everybody follow me there? Okay.
Parallel is the opposite. If you wire
them parallel, you group all your
positives together
and all your negatives together and then
wire them to the terminal blocks
separately. When you do that, the
ampacity increases and the voltage
remains constant.
Like I said, 50/50 chance. And this is
all going to be very pertinent when we
get to that solar panel.
And then the most importantest thing is
if it clicks, it fits.
That is from my homie Nate Key who got
me started in solar. That's what we
always say because when you connect
something or turn on a battery or turn
on, it will make a clicky sound of some
kind. If it does not make a clicky
sound, you have messed up.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Four things to know. Amps
time force equals watts. Series
increases voltage. Ampacity constant.
Parallel impacity increases. voltage is
constant. If it clicks, it fits. Does
anybody have trouble then four rules?
All right, cuz we're going to base
everything else off of those four pieces
of information. So, if you do not
understand and understand clearly, raise
your hand,
man. Everybody's a genius today, right?
Okay. So, now how does this work?
Well, um can you uh roll that inverter
over here?
>> Or just give me the spec sheet already.
[clears throat]
Let me get the spec sheet that work.
>> Who is intimidated by these?
Anybody? Who's intimidated by pages and
pages of electrical documents?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. [clears throat] It's like reading
a plea bar. No, we don't.
Um,
but I'm going to tell you this is like
medical coding. Anybody ever seen
medical coding for Billy? You know, it's
like hyperl. It's just encrypted data.
And once you know how to read it, you'll
understand everything. So, Parker, come
here.
Let's open it up to the specs.
So, now y'all can't see this, but I'm
gonna leave this out. Hold on. Let's I'm
going to pass around the pass one around
that way y'all can all look at them.
>> Will somebody find Hey, Joseph or
somebody will y'all grab a manual that
way pass it around and just see it? Y
>> because there's a lot of numbers here
and there's two different categories 6.5
10 KW and what you have to do is you
have to identify the one you're using
since they have different powers they
don't make an entirely different manual
they just put them both on one and
picking the correct value is the most
important thing. Um everything is just
setting up an equation that balances and
if you know how to set up an equation
and you set pick the right values it
will solve correctly every time. But if
one value is wrong, it will not work.
And so it's very debatable, but also
pretty easy once you see it. So right
here, I'm going to use the 10KW model
today. Uh we're going to charge a Tesla
off it right there in the parking lot.
Um and I'm looking at it and the first
thing I want to know, we write these on
the board.
You can erase that bottom
baby wipe.
Um, if you look at this
down here, you will see the max or the
MPPPT voltage range,
right? Does anybody know what MPPPT
stands for?
>> What does it stand for? Maximum
PowerPoint tracking.
>> What does that mean?
>> So, there's like a combination of volts
and amps that will come out of your
panel at any given point in time. It's
taking that and converting it into the
ideal accommodation for the system.
>> Correct. But I have to point this out
because nobody in here would say MPPPT
equals solar, would they? No. No. That's
why I'm pointing If you see NPPT, it
means solar. Write that down. That's
very important because you'll be looking
for the solar input and you're never
going to find it because you you see
MPPPT.
But that is the key range and this is
how you're going to start to build a
system. You have to have something to
start with and most people buy panels
and then try and match it. But this is
very important because it tells you the
voltage at which it operates. Um so will
you write down uh MPPPT
range 125 to 450 VDC.
What does that mean?
>> Right here 125 to 450
VDC.
>> Okay. VDC strangely stands for volts of
DC.
>> [laughter]
>> volts of direct current
and see once you know that even if you
don't know what MPPPT is you know that
volts DC
and especially that high is not coming
out of the battery that's what you have
to have for your solar now there's two
values there
125 and 450
and I say solar is like a carnival ride
in order to ride this ride you must be
125 volts tall Okay.
>> And you cannot be more than 450 volts
tall.
>> All right. I know a lot about this. I
have a lot of broken hearts at the
carnival growing up. [laughter]
And there's also another number that if
you look and you wouldn't see it cuz it
says max open circuit voltage. If you
look up here, you see solar inputs and
then all of these numbers. Well, I'm
starting with the voltage. We'll do
ampacity next because energy has to have
two values to be defined.
Okay.
[clears throat] So, we have 550
VDC.
Write that up there. Just put clip. Put
clip voltage. I'm going to call that the
clip voltage. It is listed as open
circuit voltage. That's right.
>> Yeah. Write clip voltage.
And then in parentheses below it, uh,
just put open circuit voltage.
So
[snorts] there's three numbers. 125,
450, 550. Confusing? Anybody confused?
All right. Oh, it's a lot of numbers.
All right. So, [clears throat]
we have to have 125 volts to turn the
machine on. If you have 100 volts, it
will not turn on.
>> If you have 460 volts, will it turn on?
>> No.
>> Who thinks it'll turn on to 460 volts?
>> I think it'll probably shift to
>> All right. This is the confusing part.
It will.
>> It will.
>> What?
>> All right. This is the the one thing
that you're going to learn is there's
always two values on your solar charts.
An operating voltage and a clip voltage.
That means this and put 550 VBC in that
means the clip voltage is 550. You can
produce energy up to 450 volts. But if
you exceed 550 volts for any reason, the
system will short. It will turn off.
That means you can float up 450, 460,
470, 480, 490, 510. You're not going to
get any more power out of it. You cannot
squeeze the lemon for any more juice,
but the system will still work. If you
exceed 550, it will click and none of
your solar panels will be producing
energy at all.
>> It sound like you're describing a BFD,
like a drive.
>> A what?
>> A BFD. A drive.
>> What?
>> Like a BFD. You're able to take in the
power and comput it how you want it,
higher or lower.
>> Yeah, that's exactly. So, that is what
an inverter does. Covered that yet, but
an inverter is just a money changer for
energy. It changes one form of energy
and the other forms of energy. It takes
energy from the panels coming in at PV
and changes it into stored DC energy and
then can take the DC and turn it into AC
energy.
>> So that's basically what the in it
inverts the energy. Parker explains what
inversions later.
Um
but with these voltages, you know how
this will work. You see where it takes
to turn on, how much you can charge it
worth, and where it will clip.
The next is our power input. Now you see
power input and there's a key thing I
want you to look for on this. It has the
letter A next to it. What does A stand
for?
>> Nobody say ass.
>> Alex.
>> It stands for amps. Now you should be
looking for something in there because
you know this is where you got to start.
You have got to get this equation every
time or you're not going to be right.
You have to get all three values from
here. And strangely, you only have to
get two values because you can find the
third one from two values. All right.
So, we know we have our voltage. But
what is our ampacity?
Now, if you look on here, there's two
different numbers. 18 A + 18 A 22A + 22
A. Huh?
Well, we're using the 10KW. So, we're
going to look at the 22A because it's
under that column. And 22 amps is our
our ampacity. We cannot exceed ampacity
ever. That is what you do not want to
do. What happens if you exceed ampacity,
>> breaker trip, wire melt, something blows
up. Ampacity is the the power behind it.
Um, like on Parker's machine, what does
the resonant fre what does the
magnifying transmitter operate at? What
voltage?
>> Um, so it operates, you can put in
between 10,000 volts or you could go up
to higher than that. It depends on the
size of the machine.
>> And so what happens when you step the
voltage up? Uh, what happens to the
ampacity?
>> It goes down.
>> Oh, why? Because we have the same amount
of watts and we jack the voltage up,
which means the ampacity has to reduce.
When the ampacity reduces, it's less
dangerous. And the voltage is
electrical.
What pressure?
>> Electrical pressure.
>> It's electrical pressure. That's why he
steps his voltage up really high on the
the magnifying transmitter so he can
send it a very far distance. Ampacity is
used to do work. Like your electric
range is 50 amps. Why? Because it's a
direct short. It's a lot of electrical
work. Now, right over here, ampacity
22 amps.
Okay.
And I'm going to tell you all this and
then I'm going to show you the easy way
that you can do it because I put all
this in computer coding on a free
program that will do it for you. But I
will teach you math before I give you a
damn calculator. Okay? That's how it
should be because you might not have
Wi-Fi one day. You might have to use a
piece of paper and your brain to figure
something out. So that means coming in
125 to 450 volts, no more than 550 and
we cannot exceed 22 amps for any reason.
All right. Does anybody have any
questions on this portion before I show
you how what it means?
No. Okay. Hold this one.
>> All right.
Now, where are the electrical
specifications on this solar panel?
>> Yeah. Now, just so you know, every
electrical device in America has to have
a data plate. Unless somebody like me
took it off to confuse you, it has one.
Okay, [laughter]
it's right here. Tiny, tiny little
writing. Okay,
will you write these down for me?
And just so y'all know, you can't see
it. Lean that forward a little bit. I
have one up here. Slide that so I can
see this.
I have one up here that you can see. See
right here. And you're going to see V A
V A W. Any guesses on what those stands
for?
>> Formula you need.
>> Amps times volts equals. See, it's
medical coding. Once you know what to
look for, W means watts. VDC means volts
DC. VAC means
>> volts AC. And they have all this VOCC,
open circuit voltage, short circuit
current, ISC, maximum power voltage,
VMP,
uh maximum power current, PIM imp. You
see, we we good right here. And then you
have watts. Um, and notice one is
smaller and one is bigger. I'm going to
get to that in a minute because that
relates back to notice we have a smaller
VDC and a higher VDC. Does anybody see
how this is lining up? Okay, so let's
look at this panel.
[clears throat]
>> Parker, will you write these down,
please?
>> So, we're going to go with the open
circuit VOC
50.85
volts.
Okay, then I'm going to go ahead and
give you the operating voltage, the
Vmax,
41.96
volts.
Then I'm going to give you we'll do the
short circuit current the ISC
11.37
amps
and the max operating current 10.61
amps.
Okay. Anybody else have any questions on
this?
No.
to this thing.
>> Yes. Yes. I'm going to show you
something. And Parker,
>> write watts.
>> Just write watts.
>> Can anybody tell me how many watts this
panel produces off of the information on
the board?
[clears throat]
>> There's a lot of information up there.
Um
You're good. Just slide it back over
here so I can show the screen.
>> All right. [clears throat]
What do these mean?
>> That's 10. Was it 10?
>> I think it was 10.16.
>> Okay,
I'm going to demystify these for you a
little bit.
Now, whenever you're doing your
electrical calculations for how much
energy it's going to produce, use the
smaller number. Just write that down.
Use the little guy. I like this phrase,
the little guy. Okay. Now, there are two
bigger numbers and two smaller numbers.
Two big uh there's two volts and two
amps. The smaller number is 41.96
on the voltage and the smaller number on
the impacity is 10.16 amps. Somebody
multiply those two numbers together.
>> 426
>> 10.61
>> 10.61 61
>> 616
>> 10.61
* 41.96
>> 445
>> Huh?
>> 445.
>> Yeah,
>> I bet you if somebody goes and looks
that says 445 watt panels.
>> Yes, it does.
>> Hot damn.
>> Secrets in plain sight.
>> There you go.
>> We got a question.
>> Okay. Is there a way to determine that
if you don't have those numbers to read
by counting sales or something like
that?
>> Well, not not that I know of. There
might be one that I do not know of. I'm
sure if I sat there long enough with
nothing to do, I could tell you
>> with a meter maybe.
>> Well, with a meter, it is going to give
us what
>> voltage output.
>> Our voltage. You got to have two.
>> You're right.
>> So, it is tougher. But to make it easy,
everything in the US has to have an
electrical data sheet. And before you
start doing anything, you have to get
the values that you need. So right here,
[clears throat] if our MPPPT range is
right here, how many panels can I put on
there?
H
>> whoa, that's the question.
>> Well, let's see.
There was some secondary information
that you needed to remember. parallel.
>> Oh, because what do we want to do? Well,
let's say if they're operating,
>> if they're operating,
>> increase your
>> and I'm going to I'm going to round up
for the sake of math. 42.
All right.
And this is about standard. Most panels
that you're going to see, the bigger
panels, I don't really mess with the
smaller panels a whole lot. I figure if
you want to set a panel, set the biggest
one you can. Um, but they usually are
operating between the 35 and 50 range.
So, so mid40s is correct. Now, if I have
one operating at 42 volts,
10.61 amps.
Okay.
[clears throat]
What happens if I hook two of them
together in series?
>> Same output, wouldn't it?
>> Well, hold on. Don't don't don't series.
If you connect in series, I take two of
these panels, put negative to positive,
and test it with a meter. What will it
read?
>> 84 volts.
>> Are we tall enough to ride this right?
>> Yeah.
>> No volts.
>> Nope.
>> Nope. Hey, and who has ever hooked up a
solar system and had voltage going in,
but nothing's charging? This was your
problem.
I learned because I had uh one panel on
a 48vt system which requires 60 and I
was cussing for two days to figure out
why it wouldn't charge. There's voltage
going I didn't read the specs.
>> So you would need three
>> at least.
>> At least now
>> so three of them. But how do we want to
minimize or maximize the input?
Okay, I'm going to show you one other
thing that I I left off
cuz this has a wattage rating as well.
It says 5500 watts plus 5500 watts.
That's kind of confusing. There's two
values there exactly the same, but
they're separated. Same thing with the
ampacity. 22 amp and 22 amp. Why? That
tells you that there are two separate
solar inputs on this.
Each one will take 22 amps and 55 watts.
If you do the math there and divide 5500
by 22, tell me what you get. I bet it's
somewhere around, you know, 450.
Okay. So, [clears throat] when we go
here, we want to get as close as we can
to 450 without exceeding 550. But in
order to do that we have to figure our
higher voltage.
You see our open circuit our open
circuit. Now just so you know open
circuit means the time when the sun is
at a certain direction and intensity the
panel will float from its operating
voltage of around 42 all the way up to
50. But you're not going to get any more
power out of it. See that's the
difference. The voltage will increase
but you get no more energy. Now, why do
you have to know that? Why is that
pertinent?
>> Because
>> our clip voltage.
>> And I'm going to show you how. Now,
you'd look at this. If you didn't know
about the clip voltage, you'd say 41.96
450 volts. Should I put 10 in there?
>> 420 volts, right? You know,
>> what about the potential? So look, if we
did 41.96
* 10 in series, that would be 419.6
volts. Check mark. Correct.
>> Ah, but you didn't think about your open
circuit.
>> Let's do 10 * 50.85.
>> Wait a minute. We're still good.
H
almost can get another one on there.
Might almost could get 11. Now, so
here's what you want to do to maximize
your solar. You want to get as close as
you can to that clip voltage without
exceeding. You want to let that thing
drink as much it'll
inverter right there will take 11,000
watts of solar an hour. To put this in
perspective, according to the DOE, the
standard of average American home takes
30 kilowatt hours a day.
that inverter under ideal conditions
will make it less than three hours. Wow.
[laughter]
Technology's come a long way. Um, and
the main reason I was here because the
capabilities and it's also like the
cheapest one out there.
>> So, it's kind of a no-brainer. But, so,
hey, we could get 10 panels on here. It
checks out. If you did 11,
you'd walk in there one day about high
noon and your solar system would be
blank and you go, "What? The sun's out.
Okay, so those are your two voltages.
The other thing I did not mention was
ampacity.
Our operating ampacity is 10.61 amps.
What is our cliff ampacity?
22. Are we good?
Yeah. Yeah, we're good. I mean 11.37
it'll float up. That's way under 22.
Now, this is where you learn how to
optimize the system because we can go up
to 22 amps, but we're only going to
10.61.
Ah, so what I would do is find another
panel for this system. Why? Because I
can't wire this in parallel. Now, what
would happen if we took the same string
that's operating at 10
61 amps,
419 volts.
What will happen if we make an identical
strength? We clip 10 more together,
positive, negative, positive, negative,
and then we take our main positive and
negative from each one
and wire them together.
What will happen?
Opacity increases, voltage constant.
That means this would then go to
21 or 21.
Hold on. Yeah, 21
22. I don't know. Somebody help me here.
22. Wait a minute. I was wrong. This is
perfect.
Holy hell.
I thought oh
the ampacity goes up to 11.3
meaning this would float up to somewhere
around 22.74
which will clip your ampacity because of
the open circuit. This one is so close,
but it is.74
over. And if you did not know that, your
system would be cutting in and out
intermittently at random times, and you
would have no idea why. I've seen this a
bunch because it's so close. If this
was 11, it'd be perfect, but it's a
little bit high.
>> [clears throat]
>> So what you want to do is find a panel
that approaches the ampacity and the
voltage as close as you can. And there's
every shape and size of panel in
existence out there. They're different
dimensions, different voltages. And just
because it says 450 volts does not mean
it operates at that I mean if it says
450 volts, there's no guarantee that it
operates at this voltage.
Why? Well, it could have a higher ampity
and lower voltage to get to 450 watts.
You have to read the electrical specs on
every single thing and it doesn't take
long once you know it, but you want to
maximize the system. Now, does anybody
have any questions here?
Good explanation. How am I doing?
>> All right. [applause]
>> Okay. Now, I'm going to show you the
easy way.
>> Parker, you tell me these values.
>> Okay.
Oh no.
>> Save the world. Can't even open
it.
[clears throat]
>> Say hello to everybody.
>> Hello to everybody. Perfect.
I'm glad you're here.
>> All right. So, this is on my website.
You can do this for free. The only thing
on this is you have to make a free login
with your email address and your email
only. And that is pertinent. Uh because
you can email yourself a professional
wiring diagram showing you how to
install your system. This is spells out.
I put it on there. Um, and this will
tell you if your system is electrically
compatible if you have all the values.
[clears throat]
And I'm going to use this one to show
you.
>> So, how many are we having on this
circuit? There's 10 solar panels.
My VMP.
All right. Your max power voltage that's
going to be, and if you look up here,
do y'all want me to use the one you can
see up here or the one over here?
>> The one we can see. Okay, I'm going to
use the one on the TV
and I'm going to tell you we won't be
able to get there quite on this. All
right, number of solar panels. Let's
see. Let's do eight.
My VMP, what is it? Anybody tell me? You
see it right here?
>> 41.96.
>> All right. What about my VOC? Anybody
see it?
>> 49.9.
>> All right. 49.9.
My max power current
>> max power be 13.11
>> 13.11
my short circuit current [snorts]
>> 14.01 No one. Now look at this. These
are 550 W panels. I didn't give it any
wattage. Somebody multiply 550 * 8
>> getting right there.
Okay. [clears throat]
>> There you go. The math checks out.
>> Now you see up here I'm wiring in
series. What happens if I wire in
parallel?
It's the same voltage. I mean the same
It's the same wattage but a completely
different voltage and capacity.
But I'm going to leave it as series. Now
this right here is if you want to add a
parallel string of the same value.
Basically you're going to wire up
another one of the same value and
connect in parallel. You just hit that
and copy values.
Now battery information. Hold on.
able to add a series in parallel.
>> Yeah, just kidding.
>> Now look, you see what's my new wattage?
>> Now, now I haven't discussed batteries
yet, but everybody know what a battery
does. Okay, the battery stores the
energy. Okay, and so we have to look on
there because the battery voltage and
the inverter voltage have to be
compatible. Everything has to work
together like the parts in a car. You
cannot put a Ford transmission with a
Chevy motor. Not going to work right.
Ain't going to bolt up. So in here, you
got to look at another electrical
specification chart.
And with the big battery stuff made it
pretty easy. It the inverters and the
batteries compared together so you know
they're going to work. When I built this
is so you could test any electrical
equipment. If you had an inverter, you
had a battery, anything, you could just
enter the the specs here and it'll tell
you it would work. So, do batteries wire
up in series or parallel?
Well, it depends. Um, you know, you have
to look at the inver specifications to
know which values it has.
It has on here on my voltage ring
between 40 and 60 volts DC.
What voltage does a 48 volt battery
operate at?
>> Anybody know? Any guesses?
>> 48 volt.
>> 51.2.
[laughter]
48 volts is like saying a 2x4 instead of
1 and 12 by 3 and 1/2. All right, that's
called nominal voltage. It's called your
nominal. So, we're going to go on here
and on my inverter, how many batteries
am I going to have? I'm going to put two
of these Nexus batteries right here. And
I look at them. Now, if my voltage is
between 40 and 60 and I have a 51.2 2
volt battery or if I have two 51.2 volt
batteries and my range is between 40 and
60, how should I wire these to make them
work?
>> What?
>> Parallel.
>> Parallel. Why? Well, what would happen?
So, each voltage is 51.2
amp hours. Anybody ever read amp hour?
>> You'll read on a battery, it'll tell you
amp hours. 280 amp hours right here.
What does that mean? Well, amps time
volts equals watt. So, if you multiply
volts times amp hours, you get kilowatt
or watt hours. 1,00 W hours is 1
kilowatt hour. Okay, that's where the
numbers come from. Now, if we wire it in
series, what's my total battery voltage?
102. Will that work? Not on this
inverter, but if we wire it in parallel.
>> All right.
Well, let's see. Now, down here, I have
have one or need one. If you do not have
an inverter and you select need one,
fellow Calc will give you the electrical
specification range for the inverter you
need to select based off of your battery
and your panels. If you have two values,
we can tell you the third. But since I
have one here that I want to use, I want
to go ahead and and put in the values
from my inverter.
All right. In here it says minimum
battery input. Oh man, where am I going
to find that?
Anybody know?
>> Right here. Battery voltage range. See,
sometimes you have to read and every
manual will be worded a little bit
different. They use different terms and
specifications. That's why I'm telling
you to look for the values. You know, a
battery is DC voltage. All right. If you
see DDC in the battery specification,
pay attention. All right. So, we have
battery minimum 40, battery maximum 60.
Oh, that'll work, won't it?
Inverter PV input minimum. Somebody tell
me what it is. Tell me the PV minimum.
What do we have to have to turn this
thing on?
>> 125.
>> Oh, okay. What's our PV input maximum?
>> 450 BDC
550.
>> Now, now
>> you have to pick the correct value.
>> So, if you did 450, you would short
yourself 100 volts.
>> Yeah. At 10 amps, that's 1,00 watts an
hour.
>> Yeah. We have short changed in yourself.
>> So, we'll put our PD max as 550 because
that's our clip. Oh, will that work?
Okay, now watch this. Notice if it's
400.
>> Okay, let's say we go 300
>> red. It would not work at 300. You see,
you have to put the voltage in here and
if it works, you'll get a green check
mark.
>> Red mean or green means go. Red means
no. All right. And then our max
capacity. Oh.
We have one problem here. What was it?
The same thing I told you there. Our
ampacity problem.
>> Now let's see if we do this
parallel.
>> Everything checks out.
>> Now that's all well and good. We know
this system will work. We can take eight
of those panels. Does it maximize? I
don't know. We do nine.
We can do nine. All right. 10.
I don't know if it'll refresh.
Um,
I think we're still good. Now the last
thing you have to select the AC output
input type or the the inverter AC output
type
>> 120 [clears throat] 240 or both because
inverters can only produce 120 or they
can only produce 240 or they can produce
both. The Apex produces both. It makes
it easy. But just so y'all know when you
have 240 go into your panel it just
splits into two 120 legs with a balance
neutral.
So, you know, if you have 240, you can
go 120. If you have 120, you cannot go
240. So, it's better just to take 240 or
both. And then when you hit submit, this
is my favorite part.
Now, we have a professional wiring
diagram showing you exactly how to hook
everything up.
[applause]
And I haven't I haven't put anything on.
I finally got Big Batteries products on
here for sale. is the only thing I've
ever listed. Uh but you know, if I go in
here, if you're going to design this for
yourself, um let's say you want a
disconnect. Well, you can take the
disconnect. You need one from your TV.
Um let's see. I want a Bluetooth
transmitter. The Apex comes with one,
but I'm just doing this for things. And
it would need to wire across the the
negative from your battery and your
inverter. Um, and notice this one has a
separate charge controller because not
all inverters have the charge controller
contained.
But if you do this contain an inverter,
now it's in the inverter. That's how the
apex wires.
>> Yes. Now with this, you can literally go
on there and enter the electrical
specifications of anything with a tag
and see if it'll work. And then you can
do this
and it just sends it. It sends it to
your email. That way you can print this
out.
>> See right there. Email successfully
sent.
>> I definitely like the box that we turn
green.
>> Correct.
>> Yes. Simplifying solar.
>> Now what you when you hit when you hit
submit and that kind of thing. Um what
what comes after that? I mean they give
you a breakdown of all the products you
need or the uh products that are going
to run that system.
>> No. So ideally
>> Oh no. Oh no. Oh no. God. Oh god.
>> Pass key. Um so it emails this exact PDF
wiring diagram to you. Now what I did
was input the solar specifications of
what I wanted to use to make sure it was
going to work. What I'm going to do is I
got a little more co. This was not easy,
by the way. [laughter]
>> What I'm going to do is put a button in
here because this is my This is what I'm
putting in Costa Rica, guys. This is it.
I put Joe's pick. Um,
so you can come down here. I'm going to
put a button here that says add the fell
scout. So, you can just click a button
and it'll pull the right values that
I've selected and it'll automatically
put it in there. And ideally what I want
you to be able to do is print off your
wiring diagram and your material and
order your materials right there.
>> Yeah.
>> Um you know and and I tried to make it
pretty easy.
>> Why are
>> Well, I did not I haven't gone I haven't
put a load calculator on there yet.
There's a lot of other parts to this.
Obviously like I could stay here all day
and teach you the whole thing, but I'm
going to try and teach you the per
enough to make you dangerous.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> And I'm going to tell you, with solar,
it takes three. It takes three. You
install one with me today, you'll get
it.
>> Then you'll go do one yourself and have
one of the worst times of your life
cuz I'm not here. We've sent the Holy
Spirit a Parker to help you. [laughter]
But but you'll you'll kind of struggle
through it. And after you figure out all
your little mistakes, you'll get that
system going. and then you'll install
another one and you'll have it down pat
and after that you can go teach somebody
else. That's really what I want is more
people knowing how to do this. I'm not
trying to sell you anything. I'm trying
to give you free information. Um
>> but but right here
that's how it works. And what we're
going to do, I'm going to go through and
just show you what we're going to wire
up today. Y'all see it on my website,
Fel's Energy. Right here, Fel's Cal. You
have to have a login to get in. um
because we have to have your email to
send you the wiring diagram. What we're
going to do out there, we have eight of
these panels.
And the power max is 41.963.
Circuit voltage is what? 50.58.
Max power
one. And then the short circuit is 11.37
and we have eight of them. I'm not going
to put a parallel string. I have one
battery at 51.2 volts. It's 280 amp
hours. Boom. All right.
I have one. All that's the same. No. Now
I just pointed this out. You see need
one.
There's my inverter specs.
These are the ampacity,
the total wattage, and the system
voltage with the battery voltage. That
way, you can look at the inverter you
want to use and say, "Huh, will it
work?" You can see that it'll work, but
I'm going to change this to to have one.
All right. Same thing. 40 60
PV minimum.
>> And this is what we have for today,
correct?
>> Mhm. This is the system we're about to
go hook up outside. I'm just showing you
that it works right here.
>> So, the PV input max was uh 550,
capacity 22, 11,000.
Okay.
>> Both. Boom.
>> Oh, sorry. Yep.
>> Contained an inverter. 11,000.
That inverter will take 11,000 watts an
hour. It takes two. Now, it takes it has
two separate 550 watt or 5500 watt
chargers, which is a little different.
Why? Because you can't exceed 5,500
watts. Now, the electrical specs tell
you that. Um, but I will say that that
this one could say
5500 and still checks. So, I I made
this. You use it for free. Put any
number you want in there. Ride this
merrygoround. That's why I built it. So,
then
This is what we're fixing to go hook up
right now. Now, we have a battery
>> and we have an invert.
>> Okay,
remember three parts. Three parts.
Parker, say inverter battery panel.
>> Inverter battery panel.
>> Okay, I'm gonna take questions in one
second.
>> But this is how it goes.
This is the bank. That's the bank
account. The panels are your job.
Okay, you work your job. You put your
hard earned energy in the bank and they
store it in your account. When you need
to take it out, it comes from the
battery, goes to the bank, goes through
your house. You understand? All right.
Now, these are the three components. And
I'm going to if anybody wants to come up
here and look at any of these, you can.
I'll let take a time to ask if anybody
has questions, if anybody wants to look
at this before we go out there. I'm
going to show you, you know, how easy it
is to kind of tell where everything's
going because now we know amps, bolts,
watts.
All right. Any questions?
>> Yeah.
Does everybody understand?
>> Hey, wow. Fell's on is on Google.
I'm going to squeeze through. Yeah,
>> I think everybody.
Thank you.
>> I'll show you how we do that. I'm going
to take this whiteboard out here again.
>> Um,
>> how we doing, son?
Does anybody have questions? I said
>> they think I'm
>> Oh, yes.
>> Question. So,
>> well, no, that's the battery.
>> So cheap.
You can get the problem is nobody knows
how to like work with paint. But I just
showed
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> Now you're going to you're going to see
what we talked about and it's Dude, I'm
telling you after you see it go series
and all the voltage data then we split
this thing and change it to series
parallel and you see the ampacity jump.
Yeah.
>> And that's it. After you hit that,
you're gonna go
>> You're gonna want to go install some
>> You're gonna want to do it yourself.
>> Absolutely.
>> Will you do me a favor?
>> I'm so grateful for you.
>> Oh my gosh.
>> I'm having fun.
>> Will you do me a favor?
>> Take this outside.
>> Yeah.
They send
us
Samar,
>> guess first. I was about to say it on.
>> Well, I'll show you. They all have a
brain called.
>> Okay.
>> Sorry. I've been covering the whole
time.
>> No, no, no. You're okay.
>> Okay.